Losing Self-Confidence and Feeling Awkward
(Questioner) I am 23 years old.
(Questioner) I would like to ask you
about self- confidence.
I used to be full of confidence
but after the military service,
as I am starting the normal like going to
school,I feel rather awkward about myself.
(Sunim) What sort of hardships
have you experienced?
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner) I don't even know
why I am like this either.
(Questioner) From time to time, I notice
myself feeling awkward about myself.
I am unable to recognize myself as myself
so I become tenuous and hesitant.
(Questioner) So, I seem to lose the trust
I have in myself.
(Questioner) I would like ask about how to trust
oneself to be self- confidence..
You are overestimating yourself.
For example, you are able to run
100 meters in 15 seconds.
This is your ability in reality.
But if you are overestimating yourself
as someone who can run it in 13 seconds.
Then will you be able to run in
13 seconds everytime or no?
Since you can't do it,
you end up feeling inadequate.
You end up thinking,
"I can't do it. I have a problem."
So, the people who lack self-confidence
or who have an inferiority complex
are actually the ones with delusion
of grandeur, psychologically speaking.
In short, they overestimate themselves.
Because of this overrating,
you make an image of yourself
that is better than yourself in reality.
So, seen from that image, you feel
unsatisfied when you see yourself in reality.
So, you end up abusing yourself.
You get dissatisfied with yourself.
The image you created in your head
is not real. This is not real you.
You in reality is the real you.
This is neither good nor bad.
It's just that if you draw a better
picture of you, you feel inadequate.
If you draw a worse picture of yourself,
you feel superior.
It's the same with me here, too.
If you didn't know who I am, but were
just curious to see what I am like
so you came to hear me today.
Since you came without much expectation,
you can end up feeling,
"well, he is not bad."
So, what does this mean?
If you came with an
expectation of 50 points
but when you actually
heard me, you gave 100 points.
Then you'd think, "wow, he is great!"
However, if you had heard of me on TV or
something and thought I should be great,
so you expected to give 150 points.
But when you actually heard me here,
you don't think I am that great.
"Well, he is just so so.
I wonder what all the fuss is about."
is probably what you would think.
So, I am the same person with
the ability of 100 points.
If you have a low expectation,
higher will be the satisfaction.
Conversely, higher the expectation,
lower the satisfaction.
Do you understand what I am saying?
So, it's to have a low expectation.
Those of you who are
dissatisfied with yourselves,
are overrating yourselves.
This is why you are
not satisfied with yourself.
If you feel dissatisfied with
your spouse or anyone else,
it is due to your high expectations.
they can never measure up.
But in this world, you or
everyone else are neither lacking
or exceeding in anything.
We are as we are.
You unconsciously keep
overestimating yourself
and as you get older,
you look at yourself in reality,
you see that you have not reached
your own expectations.
Isn't that right? This is why you
keep losing self- confidence.
You as yourself are
no lacking in anything.
You are the same as you were
yesterday, today
or when you were
a freshman in college.
But you put such high expectation
on yourself back then,
as the time went by,
you have not met those expectations
and are now feel disappointed.
So, you ought to pray in this manner,
" I am doing well. I am doing just fine."
" Everything will be just fine."
You must give yourself
these positive messages.
You will recover soon if you keep giving
yourself these positive affirmations.
(Questioner) Yes, Thank you.
(Audience Laughter)
All of you should give yourselves
these positive affirmations.
But most people give themselves
the negative feedbacks.
" You won't make it. You can't do it.
What have you ever done right?"
You always seem to give yourselves
these negative feedbacks.
Here, the parents need
to reflect upon this as well.
What should the parents
say to their children?
If the kids get bad grades,
you should tell them it's OK
and that they will do better next time.
You ought to encourage them like this.
"Oh, when I was in school,
I did worse than you do now.
But I turned out alright, no?"
With these encouragements,
the kids will gain confidence.
But what do most parents do?
They scold their children.
" You can't do it!
You can't do any better."
When they want to try something,
you say," You won't make it."
You say such things always.
Even if nobody
in the world believes in them,
their mothers ought to believe in them.
But even when the whole world believes
in them, the mother doesn't.
They become discouraged because
their mothers don't believe in them.
so, when it comes to your children,
I am not saying that you should praise
them even they have done wrong,
you need to be encouraging them.
You need to see them
in the positive light.
Don't say that they can't do something.
Furthermore, you have to give yourselves
the positive messages about yourselves.
This is how you gain self-confidence.
But most of you give yourselves
the negative messages.
But of course, it's problematic
if you are so cluelessly self- absorbed
and have the delusion of grandeur.
There are those gripped
by the notion of self grandeur.
What to say to those folks?
They need to know that
they are not that special.
But only about 10% of people
have the delusion of grandeur.
Most of us, the 90% tend to have
the self-deprecating tendencies.
Therefore, we need to be more positive.
For myself, rather than saying,
" At 60, I still have not gotten
enlightened or become famous!"
I should tell myself what?
" Many monks quit and go back,
but I am still hanging in there."
" I have not quit yet! So, it's not bad."
I could tell myself thus.
If those of you who are over 70's here,
don't you think it's a great
success to be alive still?
It's a great success. " just being
alive still is a great success!"
This is the message
you should give yourselves.
But if you think, "Gee, I am 70 already
but have not even become a senator,
or haven't made a lot of money, etc
" You end up losing confidence
and feel unaccomplished.
So, give yourselves positive messages.
Many people can't go to college.
But if you are able to go to college,
how great is this?
It's great!
There are people in wheelchairs but you
have two strong legs. This is great, too.
You have to give yourselves
such positive messages.
What is the most positive and
fundamental message you give yourselves?
When you open your eyes in the morning,
first think, " wow, I am alive still!"
Try for yourselves.
As you open your eyes in the morning,
what do you say?
" Wow, I am alive!"
Wouldn't that make you feel great?
To be alive is a great thing.
If you were on a bus on the freeway
and an accident occurred,
you survived alone out of
the 30 people on the bus.
Isn't it a great thing to be alive then?
Such a great thing occurs
every morning, doesn't it?
But you don't appreciate
such a miracle everyday.
If you can't open your eye
in the morning, you are dead.
Be happy when you open
your eyes in the morning.
Be happy when you are able to eat.
Be happy with little things.
In medical biological terms, they say
that your body produce the endorphins.
Your energy level will rise.
Your energy rises and
your face will look bright.
Even those who are not especially
good looking physically,
they can look attractive
if their faces are bright like this.
If your energy rises within you,
you will always look bright.
It's not about faking a smile but your
relationships with others will improve.
Most people are gloomy
with dark shadows on their faces.
They may be good looking but
they are not attractive to others.
So, always give yourselves
the positive messages.